Let's talk about managing spam on your website.
Allowing comments on your website is a great way to connect with your readers or clients
and build a community.
Unfortunately allowing comments also opens the door for spammers.
We have all received messages to become rich overnight or purchase unwanted products.
Comment spam happens when a spammer posts comments to your website via the blog or context page.
In this lesson we will look at how you can manage and avoid spam on your website by using the
built-in features of WordPress and using an anti-spam plugin.
Let's start with the built-in features.
By default WordPress comes with some built-in features to help you prevent spam on your
site which can be found in the settings discussion page in your dashboard.
Number 1.
Limiting the number of links allowed.
Since spam comments work through backlinks and encourage visitors to the spammer's site,
many spam comments will include a high number of links.
You may be able to catch some spam comments on your site by setting a limit to the number
of links allowed before it will be held for moderation or for an admin to approve.
Just something to take note of.
The link limit is set to two links by default but you can lower it to one link per comment.
It is not recommended to set the limit to zero otherwise all comments will be held for
moderation.
The second step you can take is to change the comment moderation settings.
In addition to limiting the number of links in a comment, you can also apply specified
words, phrases, usernames, emails etc. in the comment moderation text field to automatically
hold comments containing these elements in the moderation queue.
As you will see I have selected words like gambling, insurance, win and a link to a cryptocurrency
website.
As these are things you will often see in spam comments but you are welcome to look at previous
comments to flag certain words.
Next you can also disallow comment keys or to put it differently you can have comments
with specified words or elements automatically deleted.
It is like the comment moderation setting but here you can specify words, phrases, usernames,
IP addresses and so forth to automatically place a comment in the trash.
This means you do not need to manually move the comment to the trash from the moderation
queue.
The fourth step you can take is to disable trackbacks.
A large part of spam is trackbacks.
Trackbacks and pingbacks notify you that another blog has linked to your content and
vice versa.
However, spammers often abuse this feature by sending trackbacks and pings from spam websites.
The last step you can take in the discussion page is to select all comments to be moderated.
You can do this by selecting Comment must be manually approved.
Or you can of course choose not to receive any comments at all by deselecting Allow people
to submit comments.
Before we move on to plugins let's look at how to mark a comment as spam.
Go to comments and as you will see we have two spam comments here.
Click on both.
Cryptocurrency Mania and Win Big.
Go to the bulk action, mark as spam and then apply.
Next, another effective way to manage and stop spam is by using an anti-spam plugin.
There are many free and paid plugins that offer spam protection for your website which
you can find through the WordPress.org Plugin Directory.
Some plugins worth mentioning are Anti-spam Bee, Clean Talk or a Akismet.
There are multiple plugins to choose from in the Plugins Directory so find the one that
meets your needs.
In this example I am going to install and activate Akismet.
Make your way to plugins and click on Add new.
Select Akismet and then click on Install Now.
Wait a moment for installation to complete and then click on Activate.
Once you click activate you will be redirected to a page requesting that you set up an account
with Akismet.
Akismet is free for personal use so you can select what to pay even if it is $0.
So I will go ahead and drag the bar on the right to $0 and continue with a personal subscription.
And once activated there are a number of settings you can change for how you would like the
plugin to manage spam on your site.
Let's look at a few more security plugins to consider.
CAPTCHA is a technology used to tell robots and humans apart.
Find the right CAPTCHA plugin as this makes it very hard for spam bots to infiltrate your
website.
Lastly, spam plugins can stop and delete a lot of spam comments but it can't stop spammers
from accessing your website.
Too many requests from spammers to submit comments can slow down your site and negatively affect
performance.
A firewall plugin such as All in one WordPress Security and Firewall, WordFence, Sucuri
or Jetpack will help you block unwanted requests before they even reach your site.
These plugins will ward off automated bots and scripts from trying to leave comments.
I trust these steps will help you secure your site and intercept spammers.